<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Rocky Mountain University of Health Professions Physician Assistant Program</title>
 <link href="http://rmupap.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://rmupap.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2014-05-31T11:28:50-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://rmupap.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>David Payne</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Focus on the Roots</title>
   <link href="http://rmupap.github.io/2014/03/15/focus-on-the-roots/"/>
   <updated>2014-03-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://rmupap.github.io/2014/03/15/focus-on-the-roots</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-typical-approaches-to-learning-medicine&quot;&gt;Two Typical Approaches to Learning Medicine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content-centered&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Principle-centered &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowing the difference is critical!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A content-centered approach may allow one to pass his courses. He may even pass the boards, get licensed, find a job, and function just well enough to perform at a basic level and stay employed. However, there will be significant repercussions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
1. He will not find much satisfaction in his career.&lt;br /&gt;  
2. His understanding of medicine will be limited.&lt;br /&gt;  
3. He will consistently find himself frustrated.&lt;br /&gt;  
4. He will not have the capability to develop into an outstanding clinician.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A principle-centered approach, on the other hand, will provide the foundation one needs to enjoy a remarkable career. A career where one consistently feels stimulated, where he can challenge himself to develop further and further. Consequently, he stands as a tall, full, flourishing oak of knowledge and ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-difference&quot;&gt;What’s the Difference?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A student who is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;content-centered&lt;/strong&gt; focuses on the individual leaves of the tree&lt;/em&gt; whereas the student who is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;principle-centered&lt;/strong&gt; focuses on the roots&lt;/em&gt;. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://googledrive.com/host/0B8sxZSEkeQweQjQxa1l1dlNTaWc/focus-on-roots.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width:70%; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto; margin-top:1.5rem; margin-bottom:1.5rem;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When learning about coronary artery disease, the content-centered student pulls out the list of typical symptoms and management options and tries to memorize. The principle-centered student, on the other hand, seeks deeper understanding of involved pathophysiology and fundamental pharmacology &lt;em&gt;in the effort to make sense out of why&lt;/em&gt; those symptoms occur, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we choose certain treatments over others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When learning about physical examination, the content-centered student learns technique, because this empowers her just well enough to be checked off the list during her practical exams. The principle-centered student wonders why technique became technique. She reflects, “&lt;em&gt;Why&lt;/em&gt; do I need to use a bracing finger when using an otoscope?” or “&lt;em&gt;Why&lt;/em&gt; is it important to listen to the apex of the heart with the bell of the stethoscope while the patient is in the left lateral decubitus position?” &lt;strong&gt;Not only does she ask, she seeks out the answer&lt;/strong&gt;, even though she knows the upcoming practical exam is designed to merely assess whether she performs correct technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;major-advantages-of-the-principle-centered-approach&quot;&gt;Major Advantages of the Principle-Centered Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two major advantages to the principle-centered approach: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When one makes sense out of the material, one better retains the information.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When one strives to understand principles, one discovers connections everywhere!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes the principles underlying one disease process or treatment approach also apply to several others. In other words, &lt;span class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;focusing on the roots allows one’s knowledge base to be connected to every leaf of the tree, whereas focusing on the individual leaves supplies no such connection&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;The student who sought to understand principles during her physical examination course… is primed to absorb more content once she begins her study of cardiology.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always ask, “&lt;em&gt;Why?&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Attach meaning&lt;/em&gt; to everything you learn. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent possible, master as much physiology, pathophysiology, anatomy, basic pharmacology, and laboratory medicine as possible. &lt;strong&gt;These are the roots. Nourish them. Before you know it, you will be enjoying the fruits of your labors.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
